Ronald Schuchard papers, 1981-2011
Emory University
Ronald Schuchard papers, 1981-2011
Schuchard, Ronald.
Manuscript Collection No. 1005
2 linear ft. (5 boxes)
Papers of Ronald Schuchard, a professor of English at Emory University, from 1981-2011.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Gift, 2004 with subsequent additions.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply: Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
Biographical Note
Ronald Schuchard is Goodrich C. White Professor of English at Emory University, where he began his career as teacher and scholar in 1969. He completed his graduate work at the University of Texas, Austin, and teaches courses in 20th century British, Irish and Anglophone literature. He is author of numerous studies of modern authors, particularly T.S. Eliot and W.B. Yeats. His book, Eliot's Dark Angel (Oxford University Press, 1999), won the Robert Penn Warren/Cleanth Brooks Award for Outstanding Literary Criticism and the Annual SAMLA Studies Award for the best book published by a member of the South Atlantic Modern Language Association. He is the editor of T.S. Eliot's Clark and Turnbull Lectures, The Varieties of Metaphysical Poetry (Faber & Faber, 1993; Harcourt, Brace, 1994; Harvest, 1996), and co-editor with John Kelly of The Collected Letters of W.B. Yeats, Volume 3 (Oxford University Press, 1994) and Volumes 4-5. During the 2000-2001 academic year, he was a Visiting Fellow at Trinity College, Dublin, and a Senior Research Fellow at Queen's University, Belfast.
Schuchard has been a key figure in developing an outstanding archive of twentieth century Irish and English manuscript collections in the Woodruff Library of Emory University and in organizing the Richard Ellmann Lectures in Modern Literature, inaugurated by Seamus Heaney in 1988. He is the former director of Emory University's British Studies Program at University College, Oxford and of the Yeats International Summer School in Sligo, Ireland. He is an active member of the Modern Language Association, the T.S. Eliot Society of St. Louis, the New York Yeats Society, the American Conference for Irish Studies, the International Association for the Study of Irish Literatures, and the Grollier Club of New York. In addition to serving on the editorial boards of Yeats Annual, The Recorder: Journal of the American Irish Historical Society and Texas Studies in Literature and Language, he is a member of the advisory boards of The Correspondence of Samuel Beckett and the W.B. Yeats Drama Foundation. His research has been supported by American Council of Learned Societies and National Endowment for the Humanities grants; and in addition to serving as a Fulbright Senior Lecturer in Greece, he has been a Visiting Fellow at Wolfson College, Oxford, and twice a Research Fellow at the Institute of English Studies, University of London.
Scope and Content Note
The Ronald Schuchard papers primarily consist of materials relating to Ron Schuchard's relationship with Seamus Heaney from 1981-2005, including correspondence, drafts of lectures for the Richard Ellmann Lectures in Modern Literature, writings, printed materials, and photographs. The bulk of the papers consist of correspondence between Heaney and Schuchard (1981-2005) and reflects the planning for the Richard Ellmann Lectures in Modern Literature at Emory University, which Heaney delivered in 1988 and the friendship between Schuchard and Heaney. Also present in the papers are Seamus Heaney's drafts of the Ellmann Lectures and drafts prepared for the publication of the lectures in The Place of Writing (1989), as well as a small group of printed materials relating to Heaney and a small number of photographs.
Separated and Related Material
In Emory's holdings are books formerly owned by Ron Schuchard. These materials may be located in the Emory University online catalog by searching for: Ronald Schuchard, collector.
Additional Ellmann Lecture materials may be found in Emory University Archives, Richard Ellmann Lectures in Modern Literature records (Series 26).
Arrangement Note
Organized into five series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Richard Ellmann Lectures in Modern Literature, (3) Writings of others, (4) Printed materials, and (5) Photographs.
Selected Search Terms
Uniform Title
Richard Ellmann lectures on modern literature.
Personal Names
Heaney, Seamus, 1939-
Corporate Names
Emory University--Faculty.
Topical Terms
Irish poetry--20th century.; Poets, Irish.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Photographs.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1981-2005, Series 1; Boxes 1 - 2
  Restrictions on Access
  Special restrictions apply: Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
  - Heaney, Seamus [RESTRICTED]
  - Heaney, Seamus, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Other
  - Fallon, Peter, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hecht, Anthony, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Richard Ellmann Lectures in Modern Literature, 1988, Series 2; Box 3
  - "The Place of Writing: W.B Yeats and Thoor Ballylee," Seamus Heaney
  - "A Tower in the Ear: Yeats and Ballylee," manuscript, October 12, 1985, 28 pp. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "The Place of Writing", early draft manuscript, 5 pp. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "The Place of Writing," unidentified verse fragment, manuscript, 1 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "The Place of Writing," manuscript, 5 pp. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Introduction," Introductory remarks: Ellmann Lecture Series, manuscript, 8 pp. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "The Place of Writing," manuscript, 5 pp. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "The Place of Writing," typescript with corrections ["1st draft"], 4 pp. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "The Place of Writing," typescript with corrections, 20 pp. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "The Place of Writing," heavily revised typescript and manuscript, 37 pp. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "The Place of Writing," typescript, 20 pp. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "The Place of Writing," photocopy of typescript and manuscript, 30 pp.; with photocopied source material (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "The Place of Writing: W.B. Yeats and Thoor Ballylee," typescript, 25 pp. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "The Place of Writing: W.B. Yeats and Thoor Ballylee," photocopied typescript, 25 pp. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain: Vision and Irony in Recent Irish Poetry," Seamus Heaney
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain", early draft, manuscript, 10 pp. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain" [on Louis MacNeice], manuscript, 3 pp. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain" [on Paul Muldoon], manuscript, 4 pp. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain," manuscript, 32 pp. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain," typescript with corrections, 20 pp. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain," typescript, 22 pp. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain," photocopy of corrected typescript, 22 pp.; with photocopied source material (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain: Vision and Irony in Recent Irish Poetry," photocopy of corrected typescript, 25 pp. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "The Pre-Natal Mountain: Vision and Irony in Recent Irish Poetry," typescript, 25 pp. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell: Variations on a Theme from Ellmann," Seamus Heaney
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," [on Thomas Kinsella], manuscript, 2 pp. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," [on John Montague], manuscript, 3 pp. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell", early draft, manuscript, 22 pp. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," manuscript, 31 pp. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," photocopy with corrections, 30 pp. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," photocopied typescript with corrections, 22 pp. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," typescript with corrections, 22 pp. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," typescript and manuscript with corrections, 28 pp. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," typescript, 21 pp. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell," photocopied typescript and manuscript, 24 pp; with photocopied source material (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell: Variations on a Theme from Ellmann," photocopied typescript, 24 pp. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Cornucopia and Empty Shell: Variations on a Theme from Ellmann," typescript, 24 pp. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - The Place of Writing
  - Blue line for Scholars Press edition (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Camera ready copy for Scholars Press edition (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Camera ready copy for Scholars Press edition (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Writings by Others, 1983-1998, Series 3; Box 4: folders 1-4
  - "The Birthplace," typescript of poem with a few holograph corrections, inscribed, signed and dated by Seamus Heaney, April 25, 1983, 2 pp. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes for introduction of Marie Heaney at Silgo [Yeats Summer School], 13 August 1995 with holograph introduction written by Ron Schuchard (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Casting and Gathering," typescript of poem for Ted Hughes, inscribed, signed, August 1990 [telefacsimile copy], May 28, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "At Lullwater," typescript of poem inscribed "for Keith and Ron," signed and dated by Seamus Heaney, June 28, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Printed materials, 1988-2005, Series 4; Box 4: folder 5 - Box 5: folder 28
  - By Seamus Heaney
  - Heaney, Seamus, blurb for compact disk "The Given Note," Liam O'Flynn [photocopy] with holograph notes for compact disk "Out to Another Side," Liam O'Flynn, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "To the Poets of St. Andrews," Poetry House cards, one of four greeting card, including poems by Thomas A. Clark, Robert Crawford, and Kathleen Jamie, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "Verses for a Fordham Commencement," Irish Literary Supplement, volume 1, number 2, Fall 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "Above Respectability," [review of Oscar Wilde by Richard Ellmann], The Atlantic Magazine, volume 261, number 2, February 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "Valedictory Verses," [Composed for Craysfort Graduation Exercises, 1988], photocopied poem inscribed and signed, May 13, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "Unresting Death" [review of Collected Poems by Philip Larkin], The Observer, October 9, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "Markings," Oxford Today, volume 3, number 3, Trinity Issue, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "After the Killing," reprinted in church program for St. Augustine's Catholic Church, Galway, September 4, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Heaney, Seamus, Quotation from the opening of the Linen Hall Library's new extension, 16 February, 2000, Linen Hall Library Newsletter, Autumn/Winter 2000 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "Holding Reality and Justice," Emory Report, volume 55, number 32, May 27, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Heaney, Seamus, "Filial Closeness at Work," [review of W.B. Yeats, A Life by R.F. Foster], FT Weekend, September 27-28, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - About Seamus Heaney
  - O'Toole, Michael, "Poetic Justice," Visitor, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Fitzgerald, Mary, "A Seamus Heaney Harvest," Irish Literary Supplement, volume 1, number 1, Spring 1982 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - King, Patricia McGovern, "An Interview with Seamus Heaney," An Gael, volume 3, number 1, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - O'Callaghan, Kate, "Seamus Heaney- A Poet of His People," Irish American Magazine, May 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Graham, Keith, "Seamus Heaney's Poetic Pen Conveys 'the good, the true,'" The Atlanta Constitution, April 15, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Pattishall, Roy, "In Brief: Heaney Inaugurates Ellmann Lectures," Emory Magazine, volume 64, number 3, August 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Costa, Peter, "A Conversation with Seamus Heaney," Harvard University Gazette, volume 86, number 41, June 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Raine, Craig, "Famous Seamus," Vanity Fair, volume 54, number 12, December 1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Archibald, Douglas, ed. "Essays on Seamus Heaney" Colby Quarterly, volume 30, number 1, March 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Basney, Lionel, "Down to the Center: Seamus Heaney and His Place," The Christian Century, volume 113, number 12, April 10, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Murphy, Kevin, "The Growth of a Poet's Mind," The Bookpress, February 1999 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Browne, Vincent, "Still Finding Himself in His Poetry," [interview with Seamus Heaney], The Irish Times, March 31, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Vendler, Helen, "Heaney, the Survivor," The Irish Times, March 21, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Kennedy, Maeve, "Sutton Hoo Lays Out Its Treasures," The Guardian, March 14, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Anonymous, "Emory Houses Seamus Heaney's Life Works," Loose Canons, volume 6, issue 3, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Lichtenstein, Merav, "Heaney to Appear Exclusively at Emory This Year," The Emory Wheel, March 4, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Hammacher, Deb, "Heaney Reading to Honor Chase," Emory Report, volume 56, number 5, September 22, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Brown, Sandra, "Poet Laureate Heaney Honors Chase Tonight," The Emory Wheel, September 23, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Terrazas, Michael, "Heaney Honors Chase, Emory with Papers," Emory Report, volume 56, number 6, September 29, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - District and Circle reviews, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Smyth, Gerry, ed., "Heaney at 70," The Irish Times, April 11, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - McCrum, Robert, "Life of a Naturalist," The Observer Magazine, July 2009 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Laskey, Michael, "Great Plain Utterance," The Poetry Paper, issue 7, 2010-2011 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Other printed material
  - Brochures: Seamus Heaney Centre for Irish Poetry, Queen's University of Belfast, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Brochure: "Stern," broadside poem by Seamus Heaney (in memory of Ted Hughes), undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Catalog: "Seamus Heaney," Maggs Bros. Ltd. Catalog of Heaney publications offered for sale, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Catalog: "Images of Sweeney," art exhibition catalog with quotation from Seamus Heaney's translation Sweeney Astray, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Schedule for Ron Schuchard Pig Roast honoring Seamus Heaney, Atlanta, April 13, [1988] (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, [twelve] regarding Seamus Heaney and the awarding of the Nobel Prize for Literature, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Program: Commencement, University of North Carolina (Chapel Hill), May 12, 1996, [Seamus Heaney, commencement speaker, honoroary degree recipient] (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Program: Encaenia, June 25, 1997, celebration at Oxford University (England), [Seamus Heaney, honorary degree recipient] (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Electric Light, ticket stub for reading by Seamus Heaney, Abbey Theatre, Dublin, March 14, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Program: Emory University commencement, May 12, 2003 [Seamus Heaney commencement speaker] (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous: Fact sheet relating to writings by Ciaran Carson, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Photographs, 1982-2004, Series 5; Box 5: folders 29-34
  - Ron Schuchard, William Morgan, Seamus Heaney, Tom Flanagan at Thomas Hardy's grave, July 1982 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Seamus Heaney with [William?] Arrowsmith, Bob O'Clair, and Richard Ellmann; Seamus Heaney with Bob O'Clair, and unidentified students, April 1983 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Valerie Eliot, Seamus Heaney, and Ron Schuchard, Yeats International Summer School (Sligo, Ireland), 1997 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Ron Schuchard, Valerie Eliot, Seamus Heaney, Maura McTinghe, and Ann Fogarty at Drumcliff Church (County Sligo), Yeats International Summer School (Sligo, Ireland), 1997 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Ron Schuchard in Seamus Heaney's living room for interview for Sean O'Mordha's telecast, "W.B. Yeats: Cast a Cold Eye," January 1999 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Seamus Heaney and three unidentified individuals with poster of postage stamps featuring Nobel literary laureates; ACS from Seamus Heaney to Ron Schuchard with Heaney stamp affixed, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 36)